John Hutchins Cady Papers
John Hutchins Cady Papers
1908-1961
Cady, John Hutchins.
3 linear ft.
Papers of the American architect (1881-1967). Contains architectural records of original and restoration projects, mostly in Providence, R.I., and committee records of the Providence City Planning Commission. Also includes some books and manuscripts by Cady on architecture in Providence, and maps created in 1936 indicating the growth of Providence from 1650 through 1900.
148883
Biographical History
John Hutchins Cady (1881-1967) was an American architect and architectural historian. He was the youngest son of John Hamlin Cady of Providence, Rhode Island, and Mary Tabitha Eddy, of Somerset, Massachusetts. Cady graduated from Brown University in 1902 and became a renowned historical preservationist and architectural historian in Providence. He served as chairman of the City Plan Commission of Providence and wrote several books, including Highroads and Byroads of Providence (1943); his Civic and Architectural Development of Providence (1957) is considered a classic.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Hutchins Cady Papers consist of four series. Architectural records consist of both original and restoration projects. Committee records consist of different types of records of committees of which Cady was a member. Writings consist of literary works by Cady both in published and unpublished form. Maps of Providence show the growth of the city of Providence, Rhode Island from the year 1650 to the year 1900.
Arrangement of the Collection
The entire collection is arranged according to Cady's own numbering system.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of important and notable architects. Please refer to for a complete listing. There are also relevant items in the library's Rare Books department; please see for a listing of these.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Cady, John Hutchins.; Providence City Planning Commission.; Architects -- United States.; Architectural design.; Architectural drawing -- United States -- 20th century.; Architecture -- Designs and plans.; Architecture -- Rhode Island -- Providence.; Architecture -- United States.; Architecture, American.; Architecture, Domestic.; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century.; Historic buildings -- Conservation and preservation.; Providence (R.I.) -- City planning.; Providence (R.I.) -- Maps.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Maps (documents); Reports.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Architectural records
  - Mrs. C.L. Miller, Middletown, Conn., 1908-1909 (Oversize 1)
  - Charles Z. Eddy, Providence, R.I., 1909 (Oversize 1)
  - Andrews Building, Providence, R.I., 1912-1913 (Oversize 1)
  - City of Providence, Field Houses, 1914-1916 (Oversize 1)
  - Roger Williams Park, Providence, R.I., 1914-1915 (Oversize 1)
  - I. W. Lederer, Providence, R.I., 1915 (Oversize 1)
  - Federal Hill House Association, Providence, R.I., 1916 (Oversize 1)
  - Nickerson House, 1916 (Oversize 1)
  - Norman L. Sammis, Providence, 1919 (Oversize 1)
  - Henry C. Hart, Providence, R.I., 1921-1952 (Oversize 1)
  - Pausacaco Lodge, North Kingstown, R.I., 1922-1923 (Oversize 2)
  - John H. Wells, Providence, R.I., 1922-1962 (Oversize 2)
  - Austin T. Levy, Nassau, Bahamas, 1923-1929 (Oversize 2)
  - Miss Amey L. Willson, Providence, R.I., 1925 (Oversize 2)
  - Austin T. Levy, Harrisville, R.I., 1924-1929 (Oversize 2)
  - Arthur L. Philbrick, Providence, R.I., 1925 (Oversize 2)
  - Lloyd G. Bowers, Columbus, Ga., 1926 (Oversize 2)
  - Henry D. Sharpe, Nayatt, R.I., 1927 (Oversize 2)
  - Elliot Flint, Providence, 1928 (Oversize 2)
  - Dr. Roland Hammond, Cumberland, R.I., 1930 (Oversize 2)
  - Alfred L. Lustig, Little Compton, R.I., 1930 (Oversize 3)
  - Barker Playhouse, Providence, R.I., 1932 (Oversize 3)
  - Grace Church, Providence, R.I., 1934 (Oversize 3)
  - Amey L. Willson, Petersham, Mass., 1938-1948 (Oversize 3)
  - Henry C. Hart, Little Compton, R.I., 1932-1948 (Oversize 3)
  - Shakespeare's Head, John Carter, 1772, Providence, R.I. (Restoration), 1938 (Oversize 3)
  - Thomas Clemence House, Johnston, R.I. (Restoration), 1938-1939 (Oversize 3)
  - Clarke Freeman, Bristol, R,I., 1939 (Oversize 3)
  - Edward P. Jastram, Little Compton, R.I., 1939-1946 (Oversize 3)
  - Miss Alice M. Comstock, Smithfield, R.I., 1937-1939 (Oversize 3)
  - John H. Wells, South Kingstown, R.I., 1941 (Oversize 4)
  - Swan Point Cemetery, Providence, R.I., 1947 (Oversize 4)
  - World War II Memorial, Providence, R.I., 1950 (Oversize 4)
  - Market House, Providence, R.I., 1915-1950 (Oversize 4)
  - "Cajacet," Capt. Paine House, Jamestown, R.I., 1949-1952 (Oversize 4)
  - Cocumscussuc, "Smith's Castle," Wickford, R.I. (Restoration), 1948-1957 (Oversize 4)
  - Miss Alice M. Comstock, Little Compton, R.I., 1951 (Oversize 4)
  - The Old Stone Bank, 1953 (Oversize 4)
  - Robert A. Appleton, Rehoboth, Mass., 1953 (Oversize 4)
  - Home for Aged Men and Aged Couples, Providence, R.I., 1954 (Oversize 4)
  - Thomas Poynton Ives House, Providence, R.I. (Restoration), 1954-1959 (Oversize 5)
  - Round Top Church, Providence, R.I. (Restoration), 1959 (Oversize 5)
- Committee records
  - Providence City Plan Commission, 1913-1930; 2 folders (Oversize 5)
  - Providence City Plan Commission and Its Advisory Committee, 1931-1935; 2 folders (Oversize 5)
  - Providence City Plan Commission, 1936-1941; 3 folders (Oversize 5)
  - Providence City Plan Commission Final Records Before Reorganization, 1942-1945 (Oversize 5)
  - The Proprietors of Swan Point Cemetery, Providence, R.I., 1931-1964 (Oversize 6)
  - Governor's Planning Board, Dec., 1934-March, 1935 (Oversize 6)
  - State Planning Board, May, 1935-Jan., 1938 (Oversize 6)
  - A.I.A. Committee on Historic Buildings, 1953-1960 (Oversize 6)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Walks Around Providence (Oversize 6)
    - Highroads and Byroads of Providence (Oversize 6)
    - Rhode Island Boundaries, 1636-1936 (Oversize 6)
    - The Civic and Architectural Development of Providence (Oversize 6)
  - Literary Manuscripts (typescripts)
    - I, 1933-1949 (Oversize 6)
    - II, 1947-1952 (Oversize 6)
    - III, 1955-1961 (Oversize 6)
- Maps of Providence
  - 1650-1900, created in 1936 (Oversize 7)